手机和电车里，看似安静的锂电池，其实每一秒都在进行化学反应。它没有齿轮，却能把储存的能量，持续变成电流。
Inside phones and EVs, lithium batteries quietly run chemical reactions every second, turning stored energy into electric current.
问题是，电池到底怎样给设备供电？插上充电器后，里面又发生了什么？更关键的是，为什么它能反复充电，却还是会慢慢衰减？
How does a battery power a device, what changes while charging, and why does it eventually lose capacity?
答案藏在电池内部的三条通道里：电子走外部电路，锂离子走电池内部。它们分开行动，却必须始终保持配合。
The answer lies in two coordinated paths: electrons use the external circuit while lithium ions travel inside the battery.
先从最熟悉的电流说起。电子从负极出发，流过手机的芯片、屏幕和扬声器，最后抵达正极。这个流动，就是设备工作的直接来源。
Electrons leave the negative terminal, power the phone's components, and arrive at the positive terminal. That flow runs the device.
在锂离子电池里，负极通常是石墨。石墨像一本层层叠起的书，锂原子可以被安稳地夹在这些碳层之间。
The negative electrode is usually graphite. Its stacked carbon layers can safely host lithium atoms.
当电池开始放电，石墨层里的锂会离开原位。它失去一个电子，自己变成带正电的锂离子。电子则被送进外部电路。
During discharge, lithium leaves the graphite, becomes a positively charged ion, and releases an electron into the external circuit.
大量锂原子同时释放电子，就形成了持续的电流。不过，电子不能只跑一边。否则正负电荷越积越多，反而会把后续电子挡住。
Many lithium atoms releasing electrons create current, but charge cannot keep accumulating on either side or the flow will stop.
所以，电池还需要另一条路。锂离子穿过电解液，从负极迁移到正极；电子却不能穿过这里，只能老老实实绕外部电路走一圈。
Lithium ions cross the electrolyte from negative to positive, while electrons are blocked and must travel through the external circuit.
这就是锂电池最巧妙的分工：电子负责对外做功，锂离子负责在内部平衡电荷。两条路同时畅通，反应才能持续。
This is the key division of labor: electrons do external work while lithium ions balance charge inside the cell.
到了正极一侧，材料会接收电子，锂离子也嵌入其中。原本分散在石墨里的锂，逐步转移到另一边，电池的电量也就一点点被用掉。
At the positive electrode, the material accepts electrons and lithium ions insert into it, gradually consuming the battery's stored charge.
注意，锂离子并不是在搬运电流。真正穿过手机电路的是电子。锂离子的任务，是让两端不至于因为电荷失衡而立刻罢工。
Lithium ions do not carry current through the phone. Their job is to prevent charge imbalance from stopping the reaction.
于是放电过程可以概括成一句话：电子从负极绕外面一圈，为设备供电；锂离子从里面穿过去，给整套反应维持秩序。
In discharge, electrons take the outside route to power the device, while lithium ions cross the inside route to keep the reaction balanced.
电解液因此很特殊。它允许锂离子通过，却不让电子直接穿过去。要是电子走了捷径，外部设备就拿不到电，这块电池也等于短路。
The electrolyte passes lithium ions but blocks electrons. If electrons took that shortcut, the device would get no usable power and the cell could short circuit.
到一天结束，更多锂离子已经来到正极，负极石墨里的可用锂减少，电压也跟着下降。我们看到的，就是手机提示电量不足。
By the end of discharge, more lithium has moved to the positive side, leaving less usable lithium in graphite and lowering the voltage.
充电，就是把这套过程反过来。充电器施加更高的电压，强行把电子从正极拉走，再推回负极的石墨层。
Charging reverses the process. The charger applies a higher voltage, pulling electrons from the positive side and pushing them back to graphite.
电子回到石墨，就像在另一端拉起了绳子。锂离子也会穿过电解液，重新钻回石墨层的空位。储能状态，就这样被恢复。
As electrons return to graphite, lithium ions follow through the electrolyte and reinsert into graphite, restoring the stored-energy state.
所以锂电池能反复充电，不是因为材料凭空制造能量，而是因为锂离子可以在两种材料之间来回嵌入和脱出。放电去一边，充电再回来。
Rechargeability comes from lithium ions repeatedly moving between two host materials, not from creating energy out of nothing.
这套往返听起来简单，实际却极其精密。每一层材料都必须恰到好处：既能让离子进出，又不能让两极直接相碰。
The back-and-forth motion sounds simple, but every layer must be precisely designed to host ions while keeping the electrodes apart.
正极和负极一旦接触，电子会在电池内部直接冲过去，反应可能失控，产生大量热量，严重时就会起火。
If the electrodes touch, electrons can rush directly inside the cell, causing uncontrolled heat and potentially a fire.
中间的隔膜，就是这道安全闸门。它不导电，却布满能让锂离子通过的微孔，把电子和两极材料牢牢隔开。
The separator is the safety gate: it is electrically insulating but porous enough for lithium ions to pass.
石墨和正极活性材料本身，也不擅长把电子快速分配到整块电极。因此电池里还有铜箔和铝箔，专门负责收集和输送电流。
Because the active materials do not distribute electrons efficiently on their own, copper and aluminum foils collect and carry current.
为了在狭小空间里塞进更多容量，这些材料不是平铺一层就结束，而是像千层饼一样反复叠放、卷绕，再装进电池外壳。
To fit more capacity into a small space, these layers are repeatedly stacked or wound before being sealed in the cell casing.
你看到的动画，仿佛锂离子每次都能百分之百回到原处。但现实里，总会有一部分锂被困在途中，回不来了。
Animations make lithium appear to return perfectly, but in reality some lithium is always trapped and cannot come back.
电池顶部的管理电路也很重要。它会限制过充、过放和异常电流，因为这些情况都会加快材料损伤，甚至带来安全风险。
Battery management circuitry limits overcharge, overdischarge, and abnormal current because each can accelerate damage and create safety risks.
这也解释了另一个问题：既然能来回移动，为什么电池用久了还是不耐用？核心原因，是这条锂离子通道会在每次循环中留下损耗。
If ions can travel back and forth, why do batteries age? Each cycle leaves losses along the lithium-ion pathway.
其中一部分锂和电解液会发生副反应，形成固态电解质界面，也就是常说的SEI膜。它并非全是坏事，却会消耗一部分可用锂。
Some lithium reacts with the electrolyte to form the SEI layer. It is not entirely harmful, but it consumes some usable lithium.
随着循环增加，被固定住的锂越来越多，能在两极之间往返的锂越来越少。可搬运的能量变少，最大容量自然就下降了。
As cycles accumulate, more lithium becomes immobilized. Less lithium can shuttle between electrodes, so maximum capacity falls.
过度放电同样不友好。电量长期耗到极低，会让一些材料进入难以逆转的状态。所以日常使用时，别总等到彻底关机才充电。
Deep discharge is also harmful because it can push materials into hard-to-reverse states. Avoid routinely waiting for complete shutdown before charging.
从手机到电动车，具体配方可以不同，但底层逻辑相同：一边愿意放出电子，一边愿意接收电子，中间再给锂离子留出一条通道。
From phones to EVs, chemistries vary but the core logic is the same: one side releases electrons, the other accepts them, and lithium ions get an internal path.
锂电池能充很多次，靠的是可逆的离子迁移；电池会老化，则因为这种可逆从来不是百分之百。原理并不复杂，真正难的是让它在数百次循环里，依然安全、稳定又高效。
Lithium batteries survive many charges because ion migration is reversible, yet they age because reversibility is never perfect. The challenge is staying safe, stable, and efficient for hundreds of cycles.